A Guide to the Karl Landsteiner papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff FA126
Rockefeller Archive Center
Karl Landsteiner papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff
1892-1984, bulk 1925-1943
bulk
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA126
16.6 Cubic Feet
Biographical/Historical note
Karl Landsteiner was born in Vienna, Austria on June 14, 1868, and died on June 26, 1943 in New York. Karl Landsteiner began his medical career in 1891 with an M.D. from the University of Vienna. After graduating from medical school, Landsteiner worked as a research chemist.
Landsteiner was a physician and researcher in physiology, demonstrated the dependence of immunological phenomena on chemical structure. He made an immense and lasting contribution by his studies on blood. In 1930, Landsteiner received the Nobel Prize for his research in 1900 identifying and classifying the human blood groups A, B, AB, and O. He wrote many papers on immunology, bacteriology, and pathology, especially on the chemistry of antigens; human blood groups; experimental drug allergy; studies on syphilis; etiology of paroxysmal hemoglobinuria and the etiology of poliomyelitis. Karl Landsteiner was affiliated with the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research from 1922 until his death in 1943.
Arrangement note
Arranged in chronological and alphabetical order.
Custodial History note
In 1932, Dr. Merrill Chase came to the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research and began work with Karl Landsteiner. After Dr. Landsteiner's death, Dr. Chase carried on investigations and maintained custody of the Landsteiner laboratory notes and papers until he donated them to the Rockefeller University Archives over a period of five years starting in 1980. Some of the material was water-damaged in December 1982 while in Dr. Chase's care. Dr. Chase inserted his own notes and comments into the files. During 1968, Dr. Chase collected various publications and programs that honored the one hundredth anniversary of Karl Landsteiner's birth which have been included in the collection.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 L239
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents
Types of records include: biographical material, correspondence, laboratory notes, manuscripts, reprints, and slides.
Blood; Biochemistry; Biology -- Research; Blood groups; Immunology; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Rockefeller University; Landsteiner, Karl
- Biographical Material, 1924-1943, 1978; 1; 0.8 Cubic Feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Subjects include Merrill W. Chase notes and Landsteiner estate correspondence.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged in alphabetical order.
  - [Address book], circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - [Awards, Articles on Nobel Prize], 1930-1931 1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - [Bibliography], circa 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Bibliography-Index cards], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - [Bibliography-memorial minute by Simon Flexner, staff, Austrian Commemorative stamp], 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - [Chase: Letters, notes re: Landsteiner], 1943 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - [Chase: Notes about Dr. K. Landsteiner], 1931 1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Curriculum vitae, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - [Honors], 1933-1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - [Landsteiner Estate], 1944-1948 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - [Landsteiner Estate: Correspondence], 1943 June-July (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - [Landsteiner Estate: Correspondence], 1943 August (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - [Landsteiner Estate: Correspondence], 1943 September-December (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - [Landsteiner Estate:. MWC (Merrill W. Chase) Interests], circa 1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - [Letters; Levine book review], 1943-1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - [Music-Albums-index cards], circa 1943 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - [Obituaries], 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - [Obituaries & Newspaper clippings], 1934 1938 1943 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - [Obituary Articles & Biographical Essays], 1943 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - [Portraits], circa 1924- (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - [Portraits of others], undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - [Posthumous Letters], 1943-1949 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - [Syringe], undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1915-1947; 2; 0.13 Cubic Feet
  Includes personal and professional correspondence.
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - [Letters], 1915-1927 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - [Letters], 1928-1936 August (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - [Letters], 1936 August-1947 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Letters from Ernest & Helen, 1927 1928 1932 1935 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Madsen, T. Correspondence, 1930-1933 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Subject File / Lab Notes, 1911-1984; 1925-1943; 3; 11.2 Cubic Feet
  Includes correspondence, English exercises, lab books, notes and tests, letters and transcripts from meetings, references, and scrapbooks. Lab notes and correspondence with Linus Pauling.
  - "A specific substances. Ovomucoid. Beef pepsin. A-urine. Beef submascillary glands", circa 1936 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - [A substance] "One group Specific A substances Landsteiner & Chase", undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "A substance Dialyses", circa 1938-1941 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "A substance" [notes and letters, reprints], circa 1936-1940 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "A-Urine", 1936 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "Absorption papers" [notes, reprints], circa 1937-1939 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "Adsorption", circa 1933-1934 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - [Albumin] "Beef Albumin", 1935 January (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Albumoses... Albumose is selected. Expts Egg proto & Hetero", 1930-1931 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - [Albumoses] "Egg Proto & Hetero, Horse Proto & Hetero", 1930-1931 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - [Albumoses] "Egg Proto & Hetero, Horse Proto & Hetero, Van der Scheer", 1930-1931 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - [Albumoses] Horse & egg preparation with Landsteiner, circa 1930 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - [Albumoses] Horse & egg preparation with Van der Scheer, circa 1930 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - [Albumoses] Precipitant and Inhibition, Albumoses; Van der Scheer, 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "Albumoses, Preparation of (proto-and hetero-) ", 1930-1931 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "Allergy", 1941-1942 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Allergy-KL, 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - [Allergy I] Letters, 1935-1941 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - [Allergy II] Notes, circa 1938-1940 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - "Allergy Plans", circa 1936-1942 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - "Allergy Plans...", circa 1939 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - [Allergy III] References, circa 1924-1941 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - [Allergy IV] Reprints and Articles, circa 1930 1937 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - "Allergy work, Jacobs", circa 1939 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - "Amines, [?] sera", 1927-1928 1928-1929 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - "Amino acids, Chloroacetyl and p-nitrobenzoyl, and aminobenzoyl", 1933-1936 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - "Anaphlaxis & A+-Immunization", 1931-1938 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - "Animals 3", 1924-1925 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "Animals 4", 1925-1926 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "Animals 5", 1926-1927 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "Animals 6", 1927-1928 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "Animals 7 1927-1928", circa 1928-1929 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "Animals 8", 1928-1930 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "Animals 9", 1930-1931 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Animals 10", 1931-1932 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - "Animals 11", 1932-1933 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - "Animals 12", 1933-1934 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - "Animals", 1934-1935; 1 of 2 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - "Animals", 1934-1935; 2 of 2 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - "Animal Book", 1935-1936 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - "Animal Book", 1936-1937 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - "Animal Book", 1937-1940 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - "Animal Book", 1940-1943 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Annual Reports, 1923-1929 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Annual Reports, 1930-1935 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Annual Reports, 1932-1943 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - [Anti-Q, loose page in MW Chase handwriting], 1935 November (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - [Antibodies] "One or two antibodies", circa 1933-1937 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - [Antibodies] "One or two antibodies? New Dipeptide immune sera", circa 1932-1938 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Antibodies, purified (split), 1935-1936 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "Applications" [Correspondence for U.S. immigration, employment], 1932-1934 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - "Applications" [Correspondence for U.S. immigration, employment], 1938 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - "Applications" [Correspondence for U.S. immigration, employment], 1939-1940 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - "Assistants" [Correspondence re. possible positions], 1935-1941 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - "Azo-experiments, 1925-1926" [& material from folder labeled Dr. Lansteiner [1/19/27], circa 1925-1928 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - "Azoproteins; Ester Immune sera", circa 1929-1930 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - "Azo sera, Dried", circa 1935-1937 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - "Bacterial life cycles" [reprints, 1935-1939 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - "Bean Inhibition", circa 1936 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - "Beans", 1936 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - "Beans", circa 1911 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    [Includes Landsteiner-Prasek Ms].
  - "Beans I notes", circa 1933 1938-1939 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - "Beans II references", undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - "Beans III reprints", 1923 1934-1938 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - "Bergmann method", circa 1934-1936 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - "Berwind Free Maternity Clinic, Miss Skelly (Families)", 1931-1932 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - "Bleedings, Trial, Immunization experiments", circa 1939-1942 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - "Bleedings, Trial", 1942-1943 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - "Blood 1936" [Reprints 1929-1940; Notes & correspondence 1932-1937], circa 1929-1940 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - "Blood Anti-0" [Bloods from Dr. Weiner], circa 1937-1938 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - "Blood, chicken tests and beef...", 1932 June (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - "Blood Expts", circa 1940-1941 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - [Blood groups-Important papers from MWC], 1984 July (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - "B[lood] G[roups] Rabbit Agglutinin", [circa 1929 September 23] (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - "B[lood] G[roups] Rabbits Paper II", 1931 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - "Blood, Guinea pig & Ent. G. Stokes Experiment. Rabbit blood injected into G. pigs", 1937 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - "Blood, Human with Chimps", 1931-1932 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - "Blood, Human, Group substances in", circa 1941-1942 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - "Blood, Human 0 sera on various animals", circa 1933 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - "Blood, Human, Some of the experiments of animals and", circa 1930-1931 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - "Blood, Human with Immunization from Dogs", 1931 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - "Blood, Substances from", circa 1940 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - "Blood tests for outside M. D. ['s] ", circa 1941-1943 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - "Blood work", 1939 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - "Blood work", 1940-1942 1953 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - "Blood work", 1942-1943 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - "Blood work. Data on Monkey blood paper with Dr. Weiner (J. Immunol.)", circa 1936-1939 1976 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - "1939 Blood Work w/ Dr. Weiner...", circa 1937-1940 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - "Breeding Paper. DNCL [Dintrochlorobenzene] breeding colony", circa 1937-1939 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - "Bullowa", 1926 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - "Dr. Carrel, Experiments for", 1935-1938 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - [Charge sheets], 1943-1944 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - "Chase autumn, 1938...", circa 1938-1940 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - [Chase, lab notes (folder torn)], 1933 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - "Chase. Protein digestions" [Reprints, references, notes on articles published], circa 1916 1930-1933 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - [Chemicals, lists of (with locations)], undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - "Chickens injected with various 0M, ON Bloods", circa 1931-1932 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - "Chickens 1930. Receptors. Immunizat. with dog cells", circa 1931-1932 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - "Chimps-Pptins", 1931 November (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - "Cholera", 1926-1927 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - "Cholesterol Experiments", circa 1934 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - "Cold Agglutines", circa 1926-1928 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - "Collodion Particles", 1939-1940 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - "Color Chart of Indicators", undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - "Conglutin, Serum, Goats B", 1925-1926 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - "Correa, Mendez", circa 1928 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - "Cornell" [notes & copies from articles published], circa 1930-1936 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - "Current" [Chemical notes], circa 1937-1940 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - "Current Work...", 1941 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - "Cutter lecture", undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
    [Includes typescript "Immunochemical specifity"].
  - "Das meisterschafts System [English Exercises] ", undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - [Data], circa 1929-1931; 1 of 2 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - [Data], circa 1929-1931; 2 of 2 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - "Denaturization of serum albumin, new experiments on horse serum, globulins, horse serum albumins", circa 1940-1941 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - "Deuteroalbulose A serological tests, fractionation; sheep & pig", 1933 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - "Deutero B, Deutero C, Peptones (sheep serum, digests) ", circa 1933-1934 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - "Dialyzing membrane, Investigations into the use of cellophane as a ultrafiltration constitution of benzol derivitives. Preparation of collodion bags for dialysis", 1932 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Die spezifizdat der serologischen Reactionen [figure and KL index], undated (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - "Digest, Edestin", circa 1934 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - "Digests, loose sheets 1911", circa 1932-1934 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - "Digest, Peptic Euglobun and Albumin Sheep", Fall 1932 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - "Digest, Pig Serum", circa 1932 October-1933 May (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - "Digest, Sheep whole serum Dec 2, 1932, batches 8, 9, 10, 11 May 1933, Also[?] Apr 1932, Sheep protoambulose Dec 1933" (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - "Donors duplicate", circa 1929 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - "Double Compound serological test", circa 1935-1937 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - "Duplicate Miscellaneous Expts II Diazotized Substances Book 15", 1935 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - "Duplicates Nitrochlor. compounds. Specificity tests Book 13", 1934-1935 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - [Dye Experiments. Loose papers, notes], circa 1933-1934 1937 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - "Early experiments LD 1930 Cat isolpins, poled rabbit ssa; indin decalf n'protocols", circa 1928-1930 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - "Egg Albumins", 1938 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - "English Expressions" [notebook], undated (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - "Esperanto" ["Bulteno de la jurmeicina Instituto de la medicina Facultato de Nogasaki, Japanlando." Vol. 4, No. 1 & 2, Aug, Oct 1932] (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - "Esperanto" [T. Lumden reprint; copies of articles by Sutekiti Miyazaki], circa 1938 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - "Families, lists of", 1926-1928 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - "Families test", 1928 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - "Famous Family, tests with A2...", circa 1932 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - "[F] atty Acids, etc as Antigens", circa 1934-1935 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - "Ferment", 1926-1927 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - "Fierz Affair" [Landsteiner reprint & lab notes, 1937-1938 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - "Fierz Experiments", 1937 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - "Fierz, Nigg, Pickels" [notes, references, reprints, circa 1937 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - "Formaldehyde", circa 1939; 1 of 3 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - "Formaldehyde", circa 1940; 2 of 3 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - "Folmaldehyde", undated; 3 of 3 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - "Formaldehyde negative experiment" [Book 22], 1935-1936 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - "Forms, finished", circa 1928 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - "Forssman antigen in Horse Kidney", 1933-1934 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - "Forssman Antigen in Horse Kidney", 1935 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - "[For] ssman bacilli", 1935-1936 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - "Forssman 1930-1932 paratyphoid" (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - "Forssman 1930-1932 Paratyphoid II Shiga..." (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - "1930-1932 Forssman. Shiga Paratyphoid" (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - "Fractionation. Sheep serum. Euglobulin. Pseudoglobulin, albumin by (NH4) 2S04", 1932 October-1933 September (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - "General Index, Book 23", 1931-1935 1935-1936 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Glassware re needed, circa 1934 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - "Glycine anhydride etc buiret base Glycyl glycine etherester HCL", circa 1932 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - "Glycine, diglycyl-leucyl-glycyl, tri leucyl-glycyl glycine", circa 1933 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - [Glycine] "L-tyrosyl-glycyl glycine, l-glutauryl-glycyl-glycine Serological tests", circa 1935-1937 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - "Glycine, Leucyl-triglycyl and tetraglycyl glycine", circa 1932 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - [Glycine] "Sugars 3288"], Summer 1936 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - "Goats, guinea pigs w/shiga, Commercial sera", 1930-1931 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - "Harte, etc", circa 1939-1942 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Haselhorst [Dr G., Hamburg], 1929 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - [Hayfever, notes, references], circa 1935 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - "Heredity. (?) Subgroups Intermedials", circa 1928-1929 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - "Heredity and Races. Irregularities", circa 1928-1929 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - "Heredity duplicate M N P", circa 1928 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - "Heredity lists, MN to be published; C; Mzg; Libgm; Inter; Heredity/Nies D", circa 1928 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - "Heredity of the D agglutinin... ", circa 1930 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - "Herring milt", undated (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - "Heterogenetic left phlei", circa 1926-1929 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - "Heterogenetic horse kidney ppn. Lechithin experiments", circa 1934 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - "Hexosamine in Stroma", 1940 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - "Hirschwald correspondence fini" [Orders for books & journals from Hirswaldsche Buchnandlung Berlin, circa 1931-1940 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - "Hordein. Anaphylaxis Expts. Iodoproteins. Paratyphoid sera 1929", circa 1928-1930 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - "Imitation and Control tests" [Book 19], 1935-1936 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - "Imm. etc" [Landsteiner notebook], undated (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - [Immune sera Inventory-Booklet], undated (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - "Inhibtion of Peptide sera with albumin", circa 1930 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - [Inhibition tests, circa 1926-1931 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - "Injections, Routine" [book 6A], 1933 February-1934 March (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - "Injections, Routine" [book 6BI], 1934 April (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - "Injections, Routine" [book 6BII], 1934 April-June (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - [Injections, Routine] "Book 12", circa 1934 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - [(Injections, Routine) Tuesday-Friday Readings] "Book 11", undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - [(Injections, Routine) wed-Sat, Tues-Fri Readings] " Book 16,17, 1935-1936 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - "Iodine Expts", circa 1943 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - "Iodoform", circa 1943 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - "Iodoform etc, as sensitizers, Experiments", undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - "Irregularities", circa 1928-1929 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - "Irregularities A and AB...", circa 1928 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - "Irregularities B x O", circa 1928 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - "I.S., Experimentswith Horse, Donkey and Mule", 1941 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - "I.S., Heating of", circa 1940-1942 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - "Iso. Agglut." [Photographs], circa 1931 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - "Isophthalic acid compound", 1936 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - "Jacobs", 1934 (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - "Javert-Rh. New York Hospital", 1942 (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - "Kidney... 1934", circa 1934-1935 (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - "Kidney, Horse experiment", circa 1930-1931 (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - "Dr. Kopelhoff", circa 1935-1936 (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - "LI", 1925-1926 (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - "LII", 1926 1928 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - [Laboratory Inventories; letter from Joanne Landsteiner], 1945 June 5 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - [Laboratory techniques by MW Chase], 1940 1980 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - "Laevo-dextro tests", circa 1928-1929 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - "Levene substances. Forssman Experiment", circa 1931-1932 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - "Lechithin", 1926-1927 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - "Letchworth" [correspondence], circa 1929-1935 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - "Letchworth tests Duplicate copies", circa 1929 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - [Letchworth Village Correspondence-Loose Papers, circa 1929-1932 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - "Letchworth Village Trips", circa 1930 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - "Leucine, tetra glycyl leucine", circa 1932 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - "Lists, Duplicate of Manhattan State Hospital Letchworth Village Dr Levine", circa 1928 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - "M and N", 1930-1931 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - "M and N, Extracts", circa 1928-1932 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - "M and N" [Requests for sera], 1931-1934 (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - "M and N" [Requests for sera], 1935-1941 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - "M First observations", undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - [M, N Blood Antigens], circa 1931 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - [M, N Blood antigens, Inheritance of M and N], circa 1929-1931 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - "M, N Families x heredity 1928" (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - "M, N,P Expts. 1) early observation 2) chimps and apes; Paper 1", 1927-1928 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - "M odd[?] Races; Race Paper", circa 1928 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - [Malic acid test], circa 1929-1931 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - "Meier", undated (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - "Meier Typed Notes", circa 1932-1940 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    [Also includes handwritten notes].
  - "Membership fees and miscellaneous bills paid", 1931-1933 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - "Membership fees and miscellaneous bills paid", 1934-1936 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - [Methyl Heptine (+Oct) chlorides] "Book 18"], 1935-1936 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - "Meyer substances Miscellaneous polysaccharides 1935-37", 1936-1937 1940 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - [Microscopic slide prepared by Landsteiner], undated (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - "Miscellaneous [Immunization, complement fixation] ", 1926-1927 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - [Miscellaneous Experiments, Duplicate] "Book 14", 1935 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - "Miscellaneous notes", 1928 September (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - [Miscellaneous notes], circa 1931 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - [Miscellany], 1914 1923-1924 1931 1933 1938 1942-1943 1946 1948 1970 1980 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - "Molecular compounds and Hydrotropism literature", undated (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - [Montefiore Hospital, bloods sent from], circa 1929-1930 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - "Mucin, Hog Stomach I A substance", 1935-1936 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - "Mucin, Hog Stomach II", 1936-1937 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - "Mucin, Hog Stomach III", 1937-1938 (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - "Mucin, Hog Stomach IV. A Substance. Pepsin (autodigest) ", circa 1938 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - "Mucin, Hog Stomach V. A Substance. Special Protocols", circa 1938 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - "Mucin, VI Hydrolysis Experiments. A Substance", circa 1939 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - "Mucin, Hog Stomach. A Substance Digestions Splitting Amino Acids Jan 1940", circa 1939-1940 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - "Mustard Oil", undated (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - "Myxococcus Completed Experiments strain 8a & ", circa 1934-1936 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - "Nickel Cobalt Experiments", undated (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - "Northrup; Deutero A-3d. Deutero A-2d", circa 1933-1934 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - [Notebook], circa 1920 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - [Notebooks-Reprints], undated (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - [Notes], circa 1932 (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - [Notes & note by MWC], circa 1942 (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - [notes; miscellaneous], undated (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - [Notes to be refiled with folders re papers 283,286,365], circa 1932 1936-1937 (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - [Notes unidentified], undated (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - "Optically active long chain peptides & amines", circa 1935-1939 (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - "Ovalbumin absorption exp", 1938 (Box 20, Folder 17)
  - "Ovalbumin and digest Prod Thereof", circa 1934 (Box 20, Folder 18)